<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><description><![CDATA[An organization created by students, for students]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 22:23:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[About | Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><description><![CDATA[Message from our]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/about/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/about/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Message from our&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;span&gt;Founder&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
Hi everyone!
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I wanted to introduce myself as well as give a little background story as to how Pre-Law Shadowers was created back in March 2021. My name is Ayisha Jilani and I am a student at the University of Toronto currently majoring in Political Science and Public Law. I am an aspiring future lawyer and have always known I wanted to pursue a career in the legal field for as long as I can remember. 
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
During the pandemic, I found it incredibly difficult to find opportunities that helped me gain exposure to the legal profession and was seriously doubting what I wanted to do after my undergrad. One night, I was talking to a friend about how I wish there was a platform for students like myself to network with legal professionals, a way for us to shadow with lawyers, for example, and find out more about what a day in their career looks like. 
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Suddenly it hit me, there was clearly an opening for an organization of this kind and I knew I was not the only one struggling to find something like this. With the help of support and encouragement from friends and family, I stepped out of my comfort zone and took a leap of faith. That is how Pre-Law Shadowers came to be!
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I remember worrying about how this would all work out and whether people would be interested or not. Months later, I can confidently say that Pre-Law Shadowers has exceeded my expectations and rapidly grown to where it is today. We have also hired an amazing team of dedicated individuals, who I am very proud to be working with. 
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
I hope you become a part of the Pre-Law Shadowers community, and that we can help you with your future academic journey. 
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Sincerely,
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Ayisha Jilani</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Contact | Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><description><![CDATA[Get in Touch. If you’ve got an inquiry for a job or project,drop me a line at hello@hello.com or fill the form right here.]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/contact/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/contact/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Get in Touch.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve got an inquiry for a job or project,drop me a line at hello@hello.com or fill the form right here.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><description><![CDATA[Pre-Law Shadowers An organization created by students, for students]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Pre-Law Shadowers&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An organization created by students, for students&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/join/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/join/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;!-- ---
title: &apos;Join | Pre-Law Shadowers&apos;
template: &apos;join-template&apos;
--- --&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Events | Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/sessions/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/sessions/</guid><content:encoded></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Team | Pre-Law Shadowers]]></title><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/team/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/team/</guid><content:encoded></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Where Should You Work? Comparing Law Firms vs. Working In-House]]></title><description><![CDATA[It may seem as though working for the government or private law firms are the only two routes one can pursue after graduating law school yet…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/857b3/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIEAwX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAv/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB5FtiRWQwn//EABkQAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAxESIf/aAAgBAQABBQIBt6blbNigE2l6JjP/xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEgH/2gAIAQMBAT8BlGv/xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEgH/2gAIAQIBAT8BteP/xAAdEAABAwUBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARFBAhAhMTKh/9oACAEBAAY/AmaSpcnfgjpJu3//xAAZEAEAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExQYH/2gAIAQEAAT8hoQr4rsHa2cZrj2DjTUDtW1B9T//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQG8//xAAYEQACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBEhMf/aAAgBAwEBPxCYoaj/xAAYEQACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBEhMf/aAAgBAgEBPxCBs4r/xAAdEAEBAAEEAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAhQWGRMXGB/9oACAEBAAE/ELhdDgbe80P3QUsdZ3k4EmwqfcCitAMjJechgCkPAuEge2f/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyers at a desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyers at a desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/828fb/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/ff44c/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 158w,
/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/a6688/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 315w,
/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/828fb/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 630w,
/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/0ede0/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 945w,
/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/3ac88/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 1260w,
/static/d91dc93294d3f5aeb652911085c48456/857b3/where-should-you-work-comparing-law-firms-vs-working-in-house.jpg 6000w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem as though working for the government or private law firms are the only two routes one can pursue after graduating law school yet that is not the case! For instance, one of the numerous options available to law school graduates is working as an in-house lawyer. Take for example a brand new but rapidly growing corporation. Such corporations require a legal department well equipped to solve future legal issues such as compliance, risk management, and ethics. Work in such areas is distinct from operations conducted at a law firm where most of your colleagues are fellow lawyers or professionals from the legal industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legal industry has seen a pivot in the prevalence and importance of in-house legal departments. This is a consequence of the increase in corporations, in respect to both number and their sphere of influence. As a result, corporations are realizing the value in investing in their legal department, ensuring that its team is well versed in their business and is fully equipped to serve their legal needs (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To gain a better sense of what being an in-house lawyer is like, one can compare it to the field of private practice. In terms of salary, it should be noted that the average lawyer in private practice makes more money than the average in-house lawyer. Remember that the ultimate goal of these firms is to make profit, which requires their lawyers work more billable hours. Consequently, private practice typically dumps more work on the lawyers so they can make more money for the firm (2). This is an important caveat to consider when weighing the two options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regards to the type of work you’ll find yourself in, in-house lawyers lean more towards being ‘generalists.’ There won’t be much room to specialize in a specific type or nature of cases.  For example, in-house lawyers are likely to work at a large company working to solve various legal issues, with relatively smaller teams when compared to a firm full of lawyers. One can refer to such lawyers as being the jack of all trades. Contrastingly, private practice requires lawyers to serve a very large client base. Therefore, a lawyer working in a firm is likely to receive more nuanced work in the specific area they’ve specialized in. Some might even say that the cases you undertake in private practice are more intellectually stimulating than the in-house counterpart (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the similarities, the nature of the two positions can be identical. At the very core of it, both routes consist of thorough research, intense debates, and lots of writing for the purposes of solving legal issues (4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page, Michael. Which Legal Practice Suits You? In-house or Private Firm?. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelpage.ca/advice/career-advice/growing-your-career/which-legal-practice-suits-you-house-or-private-firm&quot;&gt;https://www.michaelpage.ca/advice/career-advice/growing-your-career/which-legal-practice-suits-you-house-or-private-firm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gardiner, Heather. (2011). The big dilemma: law firm vs. in-house. Canadian Lawyer Mag. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canadianlawyermag.com/news/general/the-big-dilemma-law-firm-vs-in-house/268396&quot;&gt;https://www.canadianlawyermag.com/news/general/the-big-dilemma-law-firm-vs-in-house/268396&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Davila, Denise. (2018). Starting in-house: Pros and Cons. San Diego County Bar Association. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdcba.org/?pg=FTR-Mar-2018-5&quot;&gt;https://www.sdcba.org/?pg=FTR-Mar-2018-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Lawyers’ Lawyers. (2019). The Practice – Harvard Law 5, no. 4. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepractice.law.harvard.edu/article/the-lawyers-lawyers/&quot;&gt;https://thepractice.law.harvard.edu/article/the-lawyers-lawyers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kim Sanchez&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Blockchain & Law - The Challenge of Anonymity]]></title><description><![CDATA[According to Collin’s Dictionary, 2021’s word of the year was “non-fungible token,” otherwise more commonly referred to as NFT (2). As one…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/caf7d/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAACA//EABYBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECA//aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABTyQcT2bKv//EABkQAQADAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAAhEhMv/aAAgBAQABBQK08iuvJm1Z/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEBH/2gAIAQMBAT8Bp//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQ/9oACAECAQE/AQn/xAAaEAACAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIQESFR/9oACAEBAAY/AsD7bkbP/8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERMSFBUf/aAAgBAQABPyHYQrEuiDKBNOmS3Yrbyk//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEEPv/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARD/2gAIAQMBAT8QUz//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEP/aAAgBAgEBPxAIWf/EABwQAQEAAwEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAERACFBMVFxgf/aAAgBAQABPxC6ArNpv9uXjWhej7yuJHyYD9XYR+cTtlwcNzKNXxeGf//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Physical representation of cryptocurrencies&quot;
        title=&quot;Physical representation of cryptocurrencies&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/828fb/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/ff44c/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg 158w,
/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/a6688/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg 315w,
/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/828fb/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg 630w,
/static/a7b4d1e755d81f628fb1efc09cdcb726/caf7d/blockchain-and-law-the-challenge-of-anonymity.jpg 784w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Collin’s Dictionary, 2021’s word of the year was “non-fungible token,” otherwise more commonly referred to as NFT (2). As one would expect, the popularization of blockchain jargon points to the extensive influence of the metaverse, digital art, and cryptocurrency in contemporary society. Blockchain is a decentralized digital algorithm that is primarily used to buy and trade cryptocurrency. In a perfect world, the anonymity of blockchain technology increases user privacy and reduces cost. If blockchain technology is imbued with a number of benefits, how could blockchain and cryptocurrency truly be problematic? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, here’s the complication: blockchain is entirely unregulated and unfairly taxed. Without sufficient fintech (financial technology) regulation, the very function of criminal law and taxation dwindle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Taxation:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the Bank of Canada Act, cryptocurrency does not qualify as legal tender, and as a result, such assets are retracted from classifying as legitimate “money” (3). Instead, cryptocurrency is treated as a commodity or security, regulated by the Canadian Security Administrators (CSA) (3). This implies that cryptocurrency exchanges are treated as barter exchanges, as per the Canadian Revenue Agency (CRA) (4). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent statistics estimate that the total transaction value of digital payment is expected to reach $6.7 trillion by 2023 (5). Needless to state, this means that a towering amount of wealth is accumulated through the medium of blockchain technology. The lack of taxation enables the rich to continue growing richer without an obligation to promote income or wealth distribution; since cryptocurrency purchases are untaxed, the Canadian government solely taxes crypto holders through capital gains or business income taxes (4). Unlike standard income taxes, capital gains taxes are significantly lower; capital gains tax only levies from 50% of the net profit gained through crypto assets (4). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with cryptocurrency is not taxation itself, but rather, the lack of stringent regulations that monitor whether Canadians are reporting crypto assets on their annual tax returns. Tax evasion with cryptocurrency is rampant, and the CRA reports that Canada has a total of over $177 billion in lost revenue as a result of tax avoidance (1). It is blockchain technology’s anonymity that shields tax evaders from tax crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;White-Collar Crimes:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems with deregulated fintech do, in fact, get worse. Blockchain algorithms serve as the perfect platform for white-collar crimes; tax evasion, ransomware attacks, and fraud often plague standard fintech platforms such as Coinbase, MetaMask, and Binance (6). Without regulations, the perpetrators of such crimes will simply be acquitted while profiting off the illegal gains. Currently, Canadian legislation is seeking to upkeep investor protection; however, it is particularly difficult to enforce investor protection regulations when anonymity blankets any form of investigation or traceability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of laws and regulations that address criminal penalties for fintech crimes translates to a large vulnerability for investors on the platform. In the case that an investor’s funds are drained due to a faulty crypto investment, virtually no regulation or law exists to penalize the issuer or compensate such losses (6). Through blockchain technology, investor protection does not exist. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per Chainanlysis, an independent blockchain software, “$7.8 billion of the overall $14 billion worth of criminal activity is from scams” that manipulate investors into purchasing illegitimate cryptocurrencies (7). The most common type of fraud—-commonly referred to as a rug pull—has illegally garnered $2.8 billion from crypto holders on decentralized finance platforms (7). The lack of regulation to inhibit such crimes from occurring is encouraging white-collar criminals to resort to decentralized finance platforms for scams, frauds, and ransomware attacks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the crux, blockchain’s anonymity is the main challenge to enacting laws and regulations that seek to address crimes and tax evasion. Without adequate investor protection, every user of financial blockchain technology is jeopardizing their individual security. Although Canada is playing a game of catch-up with the development of digital finance regulations, the current absence of laws pertaining to blockchain technology is a threat. In essence, regulation weaves security into the fabric of anonymous digital transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canada Revenue Agency. “Government of Canada.” Canada.ca. / Gouvernement du Canada, October 2, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/campaigns/tax-evasion-no-borders.html&quot;&gt;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/campaigns/tax-evasion-no-borders.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Collins - The Collins Word of the Year 2021.” Collins Online Dictionary. Accessed February 15, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collinsdictionary.com/woty&quot;&gt;https://www.collinsdictionary.com/woty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gustav, John. “Canadian Securities Regulations for Cryptocurrency Businesses.” Sia Partners. Accessed February 15, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sia-partners.com/en/news-and-publications/from-our-experts/canadian-securities-regulations-cryptocurrency-businesses&quot;&gt;https://www.sia-partners.com/en/news-and-publications/from-our-experts/canadian-securities-regulations-cryptocurrency-businesses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jackson, Cedric. “Is Cryptocurrency Taxable in Canada.” KOHO. Accessed 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.koho.ca/learn/is-cryptocurrency-taxable-in-canada/&quot;&gt;https://www.koho.ca/learn/is-cryptocurrency-taxable-in-canada/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Juljia, A. “Fintech Statistics Showing an Industry on the Rise.” Fortunly. Accessed February 15, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://fortunly.com/statistics/fintech-statistics/&quot;&gt;https://fortunly.com/statistics/fintech-statistics/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Latest Crypto Regulation Talks | TIME.” Time. Time, November 2, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/nextadvisor/investing/cryptocurrency/crypto-regulation-talks-heat-up/&quot;&gt;https://time.com/nextadvisor/investing/cryptocurrency/crypto-regulation-talks-heat-up/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vanian, Jonathan. “Crypto Crime Just Hit an All-Time High of $14 Billion.” Fortune. Fortune, January 6, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://fortune.com/2022/01/06/crypto-crime-all-time-high-2021/&quot;&gt;https://fortune.com/2022/01/06/crypto-crime-all-time-high-2021/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ira Chandershekar&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Genetic Privacy Legislation in Canada - Intervention and Protection]]></title><description><![CDATA[Canadians—now, more than ever—are concerned about protecting genetic privacy. In fact, the Supreme Court of Canada (SCC) set precedent…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/60398/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.32911392405063%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIEA//EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAGPNxFJgv/EABoQAAICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECABESEyH/2gAIAQEAAQUCMJqa8oWNA8Z2v//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABoQAAIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABETFBIjL/2gAIAQEABj8ChYLkmixvUemf/8QAHBABAAIBBQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBYYHB/9oACAEBAAE/IXlFDVzAAp1A2d2cCQdbVcR2ZiL9E//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQID//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxBH/8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAER/9oACAECAQE/EI1//8QAHBABAAMAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBUYHR/9oACAEBAAE/EA1IFgxx9gc0G1I8+4zttQuo2FAUOmnhj6SyMArL6ltXw7T/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;DNA code with genetic background&quot;
        title=&quot;DNA code with genetic background&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/828fb/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/ff44c/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg 158w,
/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/a6688/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg 315w,
/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/828fb/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg 630w,
/static/d0e852fa6276dd5fe48a3054ecaef614/60398/genetic-privacy-legislation-in-canada-intervention-and-protection.jpg 804w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canadians—now, more than ever—are concerned about protecting genetic privacy. In fact, the Supreme Court of Canada (SCC) set precedent regarding a proceeding that claimed it is ultra vires for criminal law to prohibit genetic discrimination (1). Genetic discrimination refers to the act of illegally gathering or sharing an individual’s private genetic information with employers or insurance companies; oftentimes, the illegal obtainment of such information subjects an individual to unfair differential treatment. As per the Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms, all Canadians are guaranteed the right to privacy, but the private sector continues to abuse the lack of precise legal regulations protecting genetic privacy. Fundamentally, the facets of genetic privacy are twofold: protection from the illegal invasion of others and protection of one’s own private self (2). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major use of private genetic material occurs through the process of workplace testing. As a means to identify “defective” employees, private corporations demand tests from employees regarding their genetic history (2). Alternatively, genetic information is used to monitor the health of employees exposed to hazardous chemicals or work environments. Nearly 330 firms from the Fortune 500 companies have admitted to requiring employees to submit health-based questionnaires for vocational purposes (2). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the Burlington Northern Santa Fe Railroad Company (BNSF), a multi-billion dollar North American transportation company, was charged with a class-action lawsuit for developing a secret genetic testing policy (3). It was discovered that BNSF employees developed carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS) due to a hazardous work environment. To protect themselves from legal liabilities and prove that CTS was genetically-inherited, the company threatened to fire employees who refused to get blood tests; although BNSF informed employees about receiving a blood test, BNSF secretly deceived individuals into simultaneously conducting a genetic test (3). By infringing on individual privacy and illegally gathering genetic information, the company was forced to enter a settlement of $2.2 million dollars for the 36 employees who filed the claim (3). This case epitomizes the nature of genetic discrimination, this is because the employers illegally obtained private genetic information and subjected employees to differential treatment; with threats to dismiss employees on the basis of illicit information, the company exemplified a coercive business practice. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Canada, the Genetic Non-Discrimination Act (GNDA) was challenged by the Quebec Court of Appeals in a hearing at the SCC. Nonetheless, the SCC ruled that genetic discrimination “threatens the fundamental social value of equality by stigmatizing and imposing adverse treatments of individuals because of their inherited, immutable genetic characteristics” (4). The celebrated ruling underscored that it is intra vires for criminal law powers to forbid genetic discrimination. More particularly, the SCC argued that acts of genetic discrimination challenge individual autonomy, privacy, and equality (4). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada’s GNDA policy seeks to incriminate employers or insurance companies that engage in genetic discriminatory practices; however, the Quebec Court of Appeals believes it is ultra vires for criminal powers to govern genetic privacy. Before reaching the House of Commons, the controversial bill was presented to the Senate on three separate occasions (2).  As incidents of genetic privacy violations steadily rise, the need for protection and penalization against such unconstitutional invasions of privacy have increased. The Act further lists genetic conditions as valid grounds for discrimination within the Canadian Humans Rights Act and Canada Labour Code. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dale Smith, Sara Forte, Cherie Metcalf, and Carolynne Burkholder-James. “Genetic Privacy Legislation Goes to the SCC.” CBA National Magazine, October 4, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalmagazine.ca/en-ca/articles/law/hot-topics-in-law/2019/genetic-privacy-legislation-goes-to-the-scc&quot;&gt;https://www.nationalmagazine.ca/en-ca/articles/law/hot-topics-in-law/2019/genetic-privacy-legislation-goes-to-the-scc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Privacy Commissioner of Canada. “Genetic Testing and Privacy.” Government of Canada. Accessed February 20, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://priv.gc.ca/media/4144/02_05_11_e.pdf&quot;&gt;https://priv.gc.ca/media/4144/02_05_11_e.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission. “EEOC and BNSF Settle Genetic Testing Case under Americans with Disabilities Act.” Accessed February 20, 2022. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eeoc.gov/newsroom/eeoc-and-bnsf-settle-genetic-testing-case-under-americans-disabilities-act-0&quot;&gt;https://www.eeoc.gov/newsroom/eeoc-and-bnsf-settle-genetic-testing-case-under-americans-disabilities-act-0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Canada, Supreme Court of. “SCC Case Information - Search.” Supreme Court of Canada, December 3, 2012. &lt;a href=&quot;https://decisions.scc-csc.ca/scc-csc/scc-csc/en/item/18417/index.do&quot;&gt;https://decisions.scc-csc.ca/scc-csc/scc-csc/en/item/18417/index.do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ira Chandershekar&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Debunking Myths about Law School]]></title><description><![CDATA[We often see a characterized depiction of what a law school will be like. Whether we develop these preconceived notions from TV or in books…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/debunking-myths-about-law-school/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/debunking-myths-about-law-school/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/a2510/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMCBAX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABK+XJHCA//8QAGRABAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIEEQAQ/9oACAEBAAEFAi1HGzLWap5vf//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABcQAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESD/2gAIAQEABj8CjTn/xAAbEAEAAwEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhQTFRkf/aAAgBAQABPyGoafVRVJS4PJfFfs89hmcjqf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ/wAv/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABH/2gAIAQMBAT8QR//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABoQAQACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESFBUXH/2gAIAQEAAT8QacrXLvWfIOjTQBPB37ET67hCQWVVTK5IbB7GbM//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Judges Gavel&quot;
        title=&quot;Judges Gavel&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/828fb/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/ff44c/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg 158w,
/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/a6688/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg 315w,
/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/828fb/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg 630w,
/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/0ede0/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg 945w,
/static/6a721951b49a151ffc321980166fce9c/a2510/debunking-myths-about-law-school.jpg 1000w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often see a characterized depiction of what a law school will be like. Whether we develop these preconceived notions from TV or in books and movies, we all have an idea of what to expect before entering law school. However, if you research and talk to individuals who are in law school, it will become apparent that what we think we know is not true. Here are the top myths about law school you should know aren’t completely true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, one of the biggest myths about law school is that it consists of nonstop work and there is no time for a social life or ‘play’ (1). While most of your law school career can be spent studying, the key to having both work and play is balance. According to Mary Frenson of ‘Ms. JD’, “You’ll have an opportunity to blossom socially, and make friendships that will last for years, and make connections you can use when you become a lawyer” (2). Finding a balance will prove to be difficult initially, but once you slowly progress through school, you will find a balance that works for you. Thus, despite popular belief and what is shown in the media law school can be both a place of education and networking if you identify which priorities are most important (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it has also been said that law school can be a very elitist and competitive environment with how hard it is to get in (1). Law school is competitive no matter where you go, and competition does exist in law-related competitions (1). Since competition will not and cannot be avoided, competition in law school can actually be good in some ways. Competition tends to bring out the best in students and when you are surrounded by people with goals similar to yours, you will be pushed to work your hardest to be the best at those goals (1). According to The Lawyer Portal, “a proper appreciation of law school should transcend mere competition” (1). There is a difference between healthy and unhealthy competition. You can decide which is which by if the competition is to improve one’s skills or merely being competitive for no particular reason (2). Further, it is also a common misconception that law school can be elitist, however, law school is made of all kinds of people and personalities. Law schools generally accept students based on merit instead of any other discriminatory criteria, such as LSAT scores and average GPA (1). Thus, it accepts students of all socioeconomic statuses and ethnic backgrounds from around the world (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, from afar and through the media law school can come off as “too intense and pointless”. You are given loads of readings, deadlines and obligations to fulfil. There is no doubt that law school is demanding and requires hard work, but every type of school requires hard work from individuals. Spoken from law students from The Lawyer Portal, law school is a humbling but amazing journey (1). Going through all the hard work and obstacles in your journey, you gain the experience to stand on your own two feet and skills for life (1). You learn to find solutions rather than be overturned by obstacles in your way. It may be difficult to cope with initially, but it will become more manageable as time goes by (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I have only named a few of the many misconceptions people have about law school. I hope reading this took away some stress you may be feeling about going to law school. The important thing to note here is to never give up. As any situation goes, things may not go your way in the beginning, but as time goes by you will find your way and what works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ford, Isabella. “5 Biggest Myths About Law School.” The Lawyer Portal, July 3, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelawyerportal.com/blog/myths-law-school/&quot;&gt;https://www.thelawyerportal.com/blog/myths-law-school/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frenson, Mary. “9 myths about law school.” Ms. JD, February 5, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ms-jd.org/blog/article/9-myths-about-law-school&quot;&gt;https://ms-jd.org/blog/article/9-myths-about-law-school&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anjali Kupchand&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Oral Advocacy and Arguing in Law School]]></title><description><![CDATA[Although shows like How to Get Away with Murder and Suits illustrate lawyers to be ruthless manipulative people who constantly fight…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/c94d3/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQFAQP/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABpcH5g4Mkf//EABwQAAEFAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIAAQMREiEjMf/aAAgBAQABBQL1YfRQkSrh4uwRpv/EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAS/9oACAEDAQE/AaP/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAZEAADAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARECISL/2gAIAQEABj8CR2QudpIhr24Q/8QAGhABAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARMSFhcf/aAAgBAQABPyFGweHfs0eCowUBjKFByVgWtL2CYwn/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEK8//8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQAR/9oACAEDAQE/EBBlt//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQ/9oACAECAQE/EEn/xAAcEAEBAAICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAhQVExcaH/2gAIAQEAAT8QJEHvViY1MJUjibV9YvYCCr8wmE6hjhGW5Q8W+MYmaA6z/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/828fb/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/ff44c/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 158w,
/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/a6688/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 315w,
/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/828fb/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 630w,
/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/0ede0/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 945w,
/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/3ac88/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 1260w,
/static/831d7f760d8ec1958baac84f5e03518b/c94d3/oral-advocacy-and-arguing-in-law-school.jpg 6720w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although shows like How to Get Away with Murder and Suits illustrate lawyers to be ruthless manipulative people who constantly fight individuals in courts, it’s important consider that the portrayal of law through the media is not very accurate. Whilst there is no denying that the legal field is demanding and stressful, it is not as cutthroat as Harvey Specter or Annalise Keating may have you believe. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students in law schools spend most of their time doing research and writing, rather than oral arguments and debates. It might come as a surprise, but much of the legal practice involves tedious and repetitive tasks, most of which revolve around the practice of meticulous researching and writing (3). Majority of an individual’s first year at law school going to be spent learning about writing in an intelligible and articulate manner (3). A massive portion of the professor’s time is going to be spent teaching students to carefully dissect relevant information and analyse long and complicated cases. All the effort in 1L is meant for students to improve their ability to argue in the future. Students get to acquire the knowledge of evaluating strengths and weaknesses of specific arguments and gain an understanding of how to respond in an accurate and concise manner (3). This illustrates that law school does not put all its focus on traditional oral argumentation as portrayed by the media. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preconceived notions about lawyers have created this stigma about introverted people, that they are foolish to go into law as a career. After all, it is much easier to write up a paper and submit it in a drop box than actively participating in oral arguments where one is tested on complex terminologies and theories, while dealing with intimidating doctrinal subjects. However, it is very possible for naturally quiet and socially anxious individuals to attend law school and make it through with flying colors. Being good at public speaking is a great asset, yet it is not a fundamental requirement for law school whatsoever (2). You are allowed to be your natural introspective self and take time to process and think. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the great emphasis on oral advocacy in the media, many people who attend law schools and become lawyers, never actually even get to appear in court. Transactional attorneys, big law associates, government lawyers working for regulatory agencies, trust and estate lawyers, tax lawyers, and most in house counsel rarely need to speak in front of judges or crowds at all (3). In fact, most lawyers spend their time in front of their laptops and computers dissecting written material and writing emails, letters, and reports. Therefore, if you happen to be someone who shies away from public speaking, there are still plenty of opportunities for you in the legal field. Lawyers usually spend their time informing their clients what agreements or governmental laws require them to do, all of which is done over the phone, email or in small meetings (3). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something to keep in mind, is that law values critical analysis via reading and writing over public speaking. Many people decide to go to law school simply because they think they are good at arguing, yet that should never be the sole reason. There is no doubt that lawyers are responsible for producing creative arguments to solve complicated issues, yet there is still much more to law than continuously arguing for the sake of arguing. The job of a lawyer is to be help everyone meet the goal of fairly deciding cases by working cooperatively with others. Choosing to argue by interrupting others, attacking other people’s perspectives, and openly displaying their anger and frustration are seen as a bad sign (1). Lawyers are expected to remain committed to resolving legal issues justly rather than creating more issues through pure self-interest (1). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, many law students choose to get involved in extracurricular activities which encourage debates to build their confidence, whether that comes from volunteering for a legal clinic or partaking in Mock Trial competitions. When faced with the nerve-racking task of oral advocacy, it is important to remember that it is completely natural for you to feel jittery and nervous. Even if you happen to feel anxious, it does not mean that you are not fit to be a great lawyer. The best thing one can do in such situations, is to do their homework and come prepared. Numerous lawyers have said that preparation has been the key to their confidence and success (2). Therefore, familiarizing yourself with the case at hand, sending required documents before hearings, and being well rehearsed on what you are going to say will take you a long way in being more comfortable in front of crowds. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brooke J. Bowman, Kirsten K. Davis, Lance N. Long, Jason S. Palmer and Stephanie A. Vaughan, “Oral Argument: The Essential Guide.” Stetson University &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stetson.edu/law/academics/lrw/media/Stetson-oral-advocacy-guide-.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.stetson.edu/law/academics/lrw/media/Stetson-oral-advocacy-guide-.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heidi Brown, “Untangling Students’ Fears about 1L Oral Arguments.” Teach Law better, March 18, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://teachlawbetter.com/2019/03/18/untangling-students-fears-about-1l-oral-arguments/&quot;&gt;https://teachlawbetter.com/2019/03/18/untangling-students-fears-about-1l-oral-arguments/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stephen Metellus, “Does Law School Teach You How to Argue.” The Art of Law School. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theartoflawschool.com/does-law-school-teach-you-how-to-argue/&quot;&gt;https://theartoflawschool.com/does-law-school-teach-you-how-to-argue/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myra Mansoor&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Relationship Between the Indigenous People of Canada and the Law]]></title><description><![CDATA[The tragic discovery of the unmarked graves of over hundreds of indigenous children found at residential schools has once again opened the…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/307d7/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 75.31645569620254%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAUCAwT/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHReriMBEH/xAAZEAADAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIDERP/2gAIAQEAAQUCWzozdUZLs65WNUn/AP/EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABoQAAMAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABERAhQTH/2gAIAQEABj8CbXTUKlSLw5j/xAAcEAEAAgEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExIUFhofD/2gAIAQEAAT8hYQgUolBk9pFKDZAYERDXQizlvM//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEAMP/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPxA//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPxA//8QAHxABAAICAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAARExACFBYVFxkaHw/9oACAEBAAE/EEawEDUX9fGbwWRBc/nvCZlkSJLxMJC3S+ee8TKIdHOo3xGajs0hef/Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/828fb/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/ff44c/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg 158w,
/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/a6688/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg 315w,
/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/828fb/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg 630w,
/static/b302ac0f79ece9aa0162495f858201ce/307d7/the-relationship-between-the-indigenous-people-of-canada-and-the-law.jpg 760w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tragic discovery of the unmarked graves of over hundreds of indigenous children found at residential schools has once again opened the conversation surrounding the foul treatment of Indigenous people in Canada. Now seems like the perfect opportunity to discuss the complex constitutional history of laws pertaining to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years, the Indigenous people have come to possess the same legal rights as other Canadian citizens (4). The government has amended the constitution to implement laws which protect the interests and wellbeing of Indigenous people. However, it was not always this way. For decades, officials enforced oppressive and tyrannical laws which prevented the Indigenous people from doing something as simple as leaving their reserves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadians government has always possessed control over the lifestyle of the first nations. To understand their level of authority, one can look at the ‘Gradual Civilization Act’ of 1857(4). The Act aimed to strip the First Nations people of their status to assimilate them into the larger settler population (4). It encouraged ‘voluntary enfranchisement’ in which a First Nations person would give up their status in exchange for land and the right to vote. However, given the lack of people who wanted to voluntarily enfranchise, the government began unilaterally enfranchising people through the ‘Gradual Enfranchisement Act’ of 1869 (4). Even once the Indian Act was passed, the principle of enfranchisement was still in place, where any Indian who received a university degree, became a doctor, lawyer, or clergyman, was automatically revoked of their Indigenous status (4). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to the Indian Act, the Royal Proclamation of 1763 was the only document which set guidelines for how colonial administrators were to treat the First Nations (9). It recognized the existence of Indigenous peoples and set a foundation for establishing treaties with Indigenous people. The Act established control of the Crown over the Indigenous people as it prohibited settlers from taking over Indigenous land unless it was first bought by the Crown. Essentially, it implemented a process by which the government could acquire their lands “legally”. The document was designed by colonists, without the input or consent of First Nations. Despite the existence of the proclamation, Indigenous people were continuously forced to prove their rights to land through various legal disputes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relevant Legislations, Voting and Residential Schools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian Act gave the government power over the identity of the Indigenous, their political systems, and their access to education. The legislation made it illegal for First Nations to take part in their religious ceremonies or participate in cultural gatherings. It also prohibited the First Nations to hire lawyers and bring land claims against the government without the government’s consent. Further amendments were brought in, one of which forced children to attend residential schools where they were abused emotionally, physically, and sexually. Estimated 150,000 Indigenous children were removed from their homes and forced to enrol, in which they were forbidden from speaking their native language or practising their culture. Approximately 6,000 children died at the schools, however records are incomplete, and it is expected the numbers are much higher (5). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous legal legislations have been produced to protect the rights of Indigenous people. Prime Minister John Diefenbaker drafted the Canadian Bill of Rights which emphasized equal rights for all Canadians. The bill had previously prevented Indigenous people from being denied the right to vote. Diefenbaker also repealed Section 14(2) of the Canada Elections Act in 1960, which allowed First Nations people to vote without losing their status. The Charter of Rights and Freedom also recognizes three distinct groups of Aboriginal people being: First Nations, Metis and Inuit. As stated by the government of Canada, the Charter also has the ‘anti-discrimination legislation, which exists to protect and advocate for the human rights of Aboriginal people’ (3). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indigenous people still believe that voting in federal election will not provide them with the sovereignty, jurisdiction or the right for self-determination that they seek. Over the years, the First Nations people have taken it upon themselves to represent their issues and concerns through their own political body. The Inuit and Metis groups have formed co-operatives, and band councils, which consist of an elected group, held in charge of administering federally funded programs on First Nations reserves (8) . Their goals are focused on self-government to enhance and recognize constitutionally the legal rights and powers of bands. The Aboriginal bands and band council have been granted limited powers under the Indian Act (8). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overrepresentation in Prisons and the Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main things which illustrates the inequality faced by Indigenous people in the law, is the overrepresentation of them in federal prisons. Indigenous people make up only 5% of the Canadian population, yet they account for more than 30% of federal inmate population (6). In provinces Manitoba, Saskatchewan and Alberta, Indigenous people make up about 54% of the prison population (6). In addition, indigenous women account for 42% of women in federal custody (6). They are also much more likely to be placed in maximum security institutions and more likely to be placed in solitary confinement (6). The proportion of Indigenous prisoners has been steadily increasing. Since April 2010, the indigenous population in prisons has grown up 44%, whereas the non-Indigenous incarcerated population has declined over the same period by almost 13% (7). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Prime Minister Justin Trudeau pledged to mend the broken relationship between Indigenous people across the country recognizing that “the rights of First Nations in Canada are not an inconvenience but rather a sacred obligation” (7). However, the number of inmates has steadily increased under Trudeau’s rule. Correctional Investigator Ivan Zinger, called the trend ‘disturbing’, stating the immediate need for action. He said, “no government of any stripe has managed to reverse the trend of indigenous over-representation in Canadian jails and prison” adding that “the indigenization of Canada’s prison population is nothing short of a national travesty”(6). Jordan Crosby, the director of Parliamentary Affairs for the Ministry said ‘‘we know there’s much work to do’ adding on that ‘overrepresentation of indigenous people in correctional institutions is an unacceptable situation that we are working very hard to address’ (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After decades of calling for reform, all royal commissions, national inquiries, court interventions and political promises have failed to bring about positive change for Indigenous people. As proposed by Zinger, the Correctional Services in Canada and the government must be held accountable in the overrepresentation of Indigenous people in prisons and continue to acknowledge the trauma they have endured. More attention needs to be given to matters related to their protection and overall wellbeing even by society. People should continue to use their online platforms, including social media, to educate themselves and raise awareness about the difficulties faced by Indigenous people. All Canadians should try to donate to Canadian charities supporting Indigenous communities and practice compassion as Indigenous communities mourn and share their stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chantelle Bellrichard, “Over-representation of Indigenous people in federal prisons reaches ‘disturbing’ historic high.” CBC News, January 21, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/indigenous/indigenous-overrepresentation-prison-oci-statement-1.5434712&quot;&gt;https://www.cbc.ca/news/indigenous/indigenous-overrepresentation-prison-oci-statement-1.5434712&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hilary Beaumont, “Will Canada face criminal charges for residential school abuses?” July 8, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/7/8/will-canada-face-charges-residential-school-abuses&quot;&gt;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/7/8/will-canada-face-charges-residential-school-abuses&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Indigenous Peoples and human rights.” Government of Canada. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/rights-indigenous-peoples.html&quot;&gt;https://www.canada.ca/en/canadian-heritage/services/rights-indigenous-peoples.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John F. Leslie, “Indigenous Suffrage.” The Canadian Encyclopedia, April 7, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/indigenous-suffrage&quot;&gt;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/indigenous-suffrage&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;J.R. Miller, “Residential Schools in Canada.” The Canadian Encyclopedia, October 10, 2012. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/residential-schools&quot;&gt;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/residential-schools&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leyland Cecco, “‘National travesty’: report shows one third of Canada’s prisoners are Indigenous.” The Guardian, January 22, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jan/22/one-third-canada-prisoners-indigenous-report&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jan/22/one-third-canada-prisoners-indigenous-report&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leyland Cecco, “Canada indigenous leaders divided over Trudeau’s pledge to put them first.” The Guardian, February 18, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/feb/18/canada-indigenous-first-nations-justin-trudeau-pledge-reaction&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/feb/18/canada-indigenous-first-nations-justin-trudeau-pledge-reaction&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;William B. Henderson, “Indigenous Peoples in Canadian Law.” The Canadian Encyclopedia, February 6, 2012. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/aboriginal-people-law&quot;&gt;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/aboriginal-people-law&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zach Parrott, “The Indian Act.” The Canadian Encyclopedia, February 7, 2006. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/indian-act&quot;&gt;https://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/indian-act&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myra Mansoor&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tips for Writing Law School Applications]]></title><description><![CDATA[Building your law school application takes time and effort. It can be a stressful but rewarding process once you finish and receive your…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/a2510/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMEAv/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHKLWRCUCf/xAAbEAACAwADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAgADEQQTIv/aAAgBAQABBQK6zJ2+FdSFri0qIeON/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPwE//8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAER/9oACAECAQE/AYyP/8QAHRAAAQQCAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERITECEkFxkf/aAAgBAQAGPwLXFexnJWS7OPCz/8QAGRABAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFh/9oACAEBAAE/Ic9BOiKoKL1g3L1DHOluQVKW3baWSvfJ/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAL/wD/xAAXEQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARFR/9oACAEDAQE/EHNKz//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABcf/aAAgBAgEBPxDCj//EABsQAQADAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExQWFx/9oACAEBAAE/EN0aEVXkt4ZYOtdxUpMeS+xWr2gb8+QY3UBIWMQ1Lwyf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/828fb/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/ff44c/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg 158w,
/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/a6688/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg 315w,
/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/828fb/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg 630w,
/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/0ede0/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg 945w,
/static/9c380ffc0ffdae75db700499062b5d8e/a2510/tips-for-writing-law-school-applications.jpg 1000w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building your law school application takes time and effort. It can be a stressful but rewarding process once you finish and receive your acceptance. According to The Balance Careers, a survey conducted by Kaplan Test Prep revealed that the quality of the law school applicant pool is increasing, making law school admissions more competitive even though the number of applicants has declined over time (1). Keep reading as I tell you some tips for writing law school applications based on advice from current and past law students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is important to start the application process early (1). Mark your calendar with important dates, such as when certain applications are due, so you can easily plan out how long you have to work on the application. I would personally suggest working out a schedule for when you plan to get everything done and submitted. Also, start asking for letters of recommendation months before, as you may have to wait longer than you expected to receive them, and you do not want your writer to rush them (1). Preparing and writing all your documents ahead of time will help with any last-minute issues that may arise or any stress you may feel as the due date approaches. Some tips that former law student Ashley D. Rozes had was, “show the admissions committee the impact you have made on your community, the chances you have taken, your successes, and your failures (1). Show them that if given the opportunity to attend their school, you will continue a tradition of excellence and service” (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, one of the biggest tips most law students had was to be yourself, especially when writing your personal statement (1). According to alumni Hailey Manfredi from New England Law, law schools generally approach applications very holistically, and they spend time reading each one (1). She states, “your LSAT score is a number, and your résumé does not convey your personality. The personal statement is where you get to convince admissions that you’re supposed to be here” (1). If you use your personal experience and true feelings in your application, it will be easier for you to write and be more genuine, leading to a great application. You are more likely to feel more confident in a personal statement that conveys your true self, and law admission officers can see that through reading your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, it is important to ask questions (1). Many of you applying to law school may feel lost and confused as the application process is very different and requires more effort than undergrad. There are many parts and requirements to a law school application that need to be taken into consideration. Most likely, the law school you are choosing to write an application for has many resources such as an admissions office or current students and alumni that can help guide you in the right direction and would be happy to answer any questions you may have (1). Getting clarification is important in writing the best possible application and prevents you from forgetting any vital information that may make or break your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, proofreading is a minimal tip but makes a big impact on your applications (1). Law schools not only judge you on what you write, but they also look for how you write or your professionalism. Having a clear, well-written paper with no grammatical errors is going to stand out over any other. It is important to sound professional not only in what you write but in how you write. Having a friend read over it or reading it aloud can help catch any errors you might have missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, law school applications can seem intimidating at first glance, but once you’ve mastered and considered these tips, your application will be and look a lot better, and you will feel more confident!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New England Law. “Helpful Law School Application Tips from Accepted Students” New England Law Boston, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nesl.edu/blog/detail/law-school-application-advice-from-real-world-students&quot;&gt;https://www.nesl.edu/blog/detail/law-school-application-advice-from-real-world-students&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anjali Kupchand&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Genocide of Sri Lanka]]></title><description><![CDATA[Are you aware that Sri Lanka is one of the countries in the world with the highest rates of human disappearances? This country has over 6…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/e9b2c/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 89.87341772151898%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAASABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAABAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECBAX/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAAL/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAezXPc1pUQkSAX//xAAaEAABBQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAAIDESIx/9oACAEBAAEFAshB2rV1KZGkRDFINCZz/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAASD/2gAIAQMBAT8BI//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQIBAT8BH//EAB0QAAICAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABECExAjJBQlH/2gAIAQEABj8CGuvBkvVXpuVluMKP/8QAGhABAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARIXFBsf/aAAgBAQABPyHTbWPmDFogZbuJKYpj6CuxjQqrso2USze3J95//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAHIH//xAAYEQACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAQIf/aAAgBAwEBPxAHkKF//8QAGREAAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQAQESEx/9oACAECAQE/ECY1C3//xAAcEAEAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMUFRYXH/2gAIAQEAAT8Qywbjb35NwEB3b31mKDh5BRqA0JWl+ymAWGwvBzL3YJ9MVIxWkltwGaXCXaNp/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        title=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/828fb/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/ff44c/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 158w,
/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/a6688/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 315w,
/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/828fb/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 630w,
/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/0ede0/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 945w,
/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/3ac88/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 1260w,
/static/aa6b3cf8e1f3b2a7dafe5c1251cb5421/e9b2c/the-genocide-of-sri-lanka.jpg 1758w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you aware that Sri Lanka is one of the countries in the world with the highest rates of human disappearances? This country has over 60,000 - 100,000 individuals missing since the 1980s, and Tamil people are still fighting for their liberation to this day (1). The social issue pertaining to the political representation of Tamils is ongoing in our current society. Even today, many Tamils still experience individuals trying to destroy and erase the long-standing history and culture of our generations. As individuals attempt to heal from the impacts of the Sri Lankan Civil War, the nation still reveals new systematic issues from the history of ethnic strife under international laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Historical Origins of the Conflict&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historical impact of the Sri Lankan Civil War made many minority Tamils experience discrimination, marginalization and genocide in many social and political fields. Prior to the Sri Lankan Civil War, the minority Tamil group was already struggling to exist and be accepted throughout history. This was seen in Sri Lanka’s colonial history, which revealed the roots of the ethnic conflict between the Tamils and Sinhalese that contributed to the eruption of the civil war. Ever since Sri Lanka gained its independence in 1948 from the British, the minority Tamil group felt marginalized and repressed from the majority Sinhalese group (2). The mentality of the Sinhalese group was to control the Tamils from progressing in society in which they implemented laws and policies to deny citizenship and rights to the Tamil community (3). Further, the declaration of the language, Sinhala only instead of English in 1956 increased tensions between the two ethnic groups where Sinhalese individuals sought to eliminate Tamils from various economic opportunities and expose them to Sinhalese (2). The initial struggles and diminishing of the Tamil ethnic group were the foundations of provoking the ethnic conflict to a violent state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Eruption of the Civil War&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sri Lankan Civil War comprises 25 years of conflict and over 70,000 deaths that sprouted from the ongoing segregation on the island (5). Throughout the 1950s and 1960s, peaceful Tamil protests did not bring any justice to the community, so young Tamils abandoned peaceful methods to pursue other ones (6). The period of 1970-1977 only increased the tensions between the groups, which consisted of government policies that were restrictive and discriminatory towards Tamils (4). This resulted in Tamil politicians and youths creating and joining organizations to advocate for a separate Tamil state. One of the memorable groups was the LTTE, who sought to accomplish justice and their political goal of creating a separate country, Tamil Eelam (5). The war officially began in July 1983 when numerous ethnic riots and victims arose with targets being mainly Tamils in Colombo (6). Throughout the period of the war, the majority Sinhalese people were violently persecuting against the Tamils due to religious and ethnic differences. This conflict erupted into significant hardships and deaths for many individuals, which left many Tamils fleeing to another state and many Tamil women in a more vulnerable and misogyny state. The battle came to a destructive end in May 2009 with many casualties and a demolished LTTE side from the government deploying military power to destroy the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Current State of Tamils&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long-standing ethnic tensions in Sri Lanka still persist today as many Tamils are still struggling to find justice and freedom. The aftermath of the war gave rise to violations of international human rights and advocations for charging the Sri Lankan government with genocide under international law. It was first raised by an international voice in December 2009 where Human Rights Watch pressured the international community to raise an investigation into war crimes on the issue of accountability (7). Soon after, other experts in international law also stressed for an examination in the legal case of the genocide with evidence based on the nature and extent of violence performed by the Sri Lankan government forces (7). However, certain individuals resisted the legal action against the military labour force by attempting to support and protect the majority Sinhalese ethnic group from their war crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, many political and academic institutions still fail to recognize the genocide of Tamils and the empowerment of Tamils towards addressing the injustices of the war. Both Mullivaikkal and Maaveerar Naal mark the remembrance of the deaths of militants and civilians from the war. These significant days are when commemorations in terms of rituals and processions are performed in May and November. For many years now, Tamils around the world have been honouring and protesting through hunger strikes and demonstrations for the acknowledgement and accountability of Tamils’ disappearances. The international governments’ continuous failure to support and address Tamil people’s concerns has only increased the protest towards the accountability of war crimes. Even currently, the Tamil community is still opposing the lack of political will from the Sri Lankan government in addressing the disappearances of many Tamil individuals and the injustices behind the Sri Lankan Civil War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amnesty International. “Everything You Need to Know about Enforced Disappearances and Human Rights.” Accessed June 17, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/what-we-do/disappearances/&quot;&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/what-we-do/disappearances/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ganguly, Sumit. “Ending the Sri Lankan Civil War.” Daedalus 147, no. 1 (2018): 78-89. Accessed June 22, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/48563408&quot;&gt;https://www.jstor.org/stable/48563408&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deane, Tameshnie. “Historical and Political Background to the Erosion of the Rule of Law and Human Rights during Sri Lanka’s Civil War and the Way Forward.” Small Wars &amp;#x26; Insurgencies 27, (2016): 974-975. doi:10.1080/09592318.2016.1234115.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeVotta, Neil. “The Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam and the Lost Quest for Separatism in Sri Lanka.” Asian Survey 49, no. 6 (2009): 1022-1023. doi:10.1525/as.2009.49.6.1021.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nieto, Alejandro Sanchez. “A War of Attrition: Sri Lanka and the Tamil Tigers,” Small Wars &amp;#x26; Insurgencies 19, (December 2008): 577-579. doi:10.1080/09592310802462398&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Singer, R. Marshall. “Sri Lanka’s Tamil-Sinhalese Ethnic Conflict: Alternative Solutions,” Asian Survey 32, no. 2 (August 1992): 712-713. doi:10.2307/2645364.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wikipedia. “Sri Lankan Civil War.” Accessed June 24, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lankan_Civil_Wa&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sri_Lankan_Civil_Wa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharuka Sivanandam&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Occupation of the Hawaiian Kingdom]]></title><description><![CDATA[To many, Hawai’i the dream. It is the perfect honeymoon getaway and the ideal vacation. As such, many regard Hawai’i as a state of the…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/46c54/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 68.9873417721519%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAOABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMEBf/EABQBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAD/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAWMjSUmQH//EABsQAAICAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIDAAEREyEj/9oACAEBAAEFAnD6U0s71HAMnPbZKnJ//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPwE//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPwE//8QAHhAAAgIABwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIAEQMQEiFRgaH/2gAIAQEABj8CSr7lGWy+xdXEOGGJDDfL/8QAHBAAAgIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAASEAEUFRYTFx/9oACAEBAAE/IX1xs38QBAL3kJhaC6iwEDbO5nJBj4In/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABCTz//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EAB0QAQEAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExQVFxgaH/2gAIAQEAAT8QmgqThTdH3nLHiGi8pVQ85UG0LEHDOsbQioqaOp03JcIgarvW/wB1nd6g3P/Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        title=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/828fb/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/ff44c/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 158w,
/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/a6688/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 315w,
/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/828fb/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 630w,
/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/0ede0/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 945w,
/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/3ac88/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 1260w,
/static/0cabcbfde95e5c07e05bf7833b422d02/46c54/the-occupation-of-the-hawaiian-kingdom.jpg 3436w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To many, Hawai’i the dream. It is the perfect honeymoon getaway and the ideal vacation. As such, many regard Hawai’i as a state of the United States of America. What is often not told of Hawai’ian history is that Hawai’i was a country, formally known as the Hawaiian Kingdom (1). Thus, this calls the legal and political status of Hawai’i into question; is it a country under occupation, or a state? To answer this, we would need to look at the history of how Hawaii became a state in the first place, and then look into the legal matter of its statehood, or its occupation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 400 C.E. (A.D.), Polynesians from the Marquesas Islands settled in the Hawaiin Islands, as skilled farmers and fishermen (2). The Hawaiian Kingdom reigned as an independent State (ie. Country) that had vast relations through diplomacy and trade (3). Not only did it have extensive trade agreements with the United States, but by 1882, it had also joined the Universal Postal Union (UPU), which we would now refer to as the United Nations (3). It was one of 44 sovereign nations of that time (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first European to arrive in Hawaii was Captain James Cook, in 1778 (4). More would come during the 19th century, and would heavily oppose Hawaii’s monarchy, to favour Britain’s constitutional monarchy instead (4). Not only did they have an issue with Hawaii’s monarchy, but they also drafted the first Bayonet Constitution, which would extend voting rights to non-citiens, exclude Asians, and restrict access for Hawaiians in land ownership and schooling (4). They threatened Hawaii’s king, David Kalakua, with violence to sign the Constitution (4). When Queen Liliuokalani, King Kalakua’s sister, took the throne, a new constitution that included voting rights for Hawaiians was proposed, angering the white settlers (4). They formed the Committee of Safety to overthrow the Hawaiian monarchy and annex Hawai’i to the United States (4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, on January 16, 1893, the United States invaded the Hawaiian Kingdom, leading to the overthrow of Queen Liluokalani (3). On January 17, the Queen surrendered, but with the condition that the United States will restore sovereignty to the Kingdom, with the Queen reinstated as its sovereign (3). The ending of her statement supports this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now, to avoid any collision of armed forces and perhaps the loss of life, I do, under this protest, and impelled by said force, yield my authority until such time as the Government of the United States shall, upon the facts being presented to it, undo the action of its representatives and reinstate me in the authority which I claim as the constitutional sovereign of the Hawaiian Islands” (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the condition of the Queen’s surrender of the Hawaiian Islands was such that the United States would reinstate her as the ruling monarch of the sovereign Hawaiian Kingdom. On March 11, 1893, President Grover Cleveland issued an investigation that was completed on July 17 (3). When the investigation was concluded, President Cleveland declared that the invasion of Hawaii in Honolulu was “an act of war” (3). In his full manifesto to Congress, the President essentially states that the United States aligned itself with the Queen’s enemies and recognized them as the true government of the Kingdom (3), though they were not. This manifesto was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;powerful because it showed the political aspects of occupation, and “was a political determination under international law of the existence of a state of war, of which there is no treaty of peace” (3). Without a treaty of peace, Hawaii became the United States’ forefront to show its actions to the world. However, without the President’s knowledge, a settlement was reached between the Queen and a United States Minister, that never actually implemented the reinstatement of the monarchy (3), which, as mentioned, was the sole condition of the Queen’s surrender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 16, 1897, President McKinley (successor or President Cleveland) entered into a treaty of annexation with the insurgents of Hawai’i, whose goal from the very beginning was Hawai’i’s annexation to the United States (5). In December (5), the movement to strike down the treaty had started. After several protests and meetings between the Queen, Hawaiian organizations, and senators in favour or striking down the treaty, the votes necessary for ratification were not collected, and the treaty was “dead by March” (5). However, one month later, the United States went to war with Spain, and Congressman Francis Newlands submitted a resolution to annex the Hawaiian Islands on May 4 (5). Numerous Senators and Representatives objected, but the annexation got a majority vote, and President McKinley signed the resolution on July 7, 1898 (5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in the United States, this was cause for problem, as many could not fathom how a “resolution could have the extra-territorial force and effect of a treaty in annexing Hawai’i” (5), meaning that from a legal perspective, a resolution was not enough to annex Hawai’i. Here, it becomes important to note that not only did the United States try to pass a treaty that was stricken down, but now a resolution was passed in what seems like a last resort to ensure annexation. In fact, Senator Augustus Bacon alluded to this idea, by sarcastically saying that the annexation was not possible under the Constitution through a treaty, so now the treaty had to embedded in a statute (5). The resolution is what made the annexation possible, not the treaty, though to many, the resolution did not have the jurisdiction over a sovereign nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, in a clear violation of international law, not only did the United States maintain the insurgents’ power in Hawai’i for the appearance of the government, but it also changed the name to the Territory of Hawai’i and later to the State of Hawai’i in 1959 (5), arguably as a formal announcement that Hawai’i was now a U.S. state. Thus, in 2018, a United Nations Independent Expert, Dr. Alfred M. deZayas, acknowledged the U.S. occupation of the Hawaiian Kingdom (5). According to Professor Keanu Sai from the University of Hawaii, “belligerent occupation” (1), is the term used under international law, when power is seized through an act of war (1). Not only, but the professor argues that the “illegal occupation” (1) has had extremely adverse impacts on Native Hawaiians to this day (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first way America extended its occupation was through the Hawaiian school system. Prior to occupation, the Hawaiian school system was incredibly strong, and was the fifth country to provide mandatory education, almost eight decades before the United States (6). However, the invasion led to the United States controlling every aspect of the Hawaiian government (6). The policies to Americanize the Hawaiian school system began with Hawaiian children, by passing policies that only allowed them to speak English, and speaking Hawaiian would lead to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;punishment (6). The goal of these schools was to “obliterate the national consciousness of the Hawaiian Kingdom in the minds of school children throughout the islands” (6). By forcing them to chant to the flag every morning, and cutting out their language entire, America sought to completely assimilate Hawaiians into America, through forceful policies to instill American patriotism. This policy comes under the umbrella term of “denationalization” (6), to essentially take out every sense of national consciousness from the children of Hawai’i. In fact, it became so institutionalized that children had become “strangers in their own country” (6), and without Americanization, they were often not allowed to go to high school, thus entering the workforce right after elementary (6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to American occupation, Hawai’i had an incredibly strong health infrastructure, and Native Hawaiians received universal healthcare free of charge (6). Not only did America change hospital policies, but it also sought the active denial of healthcare for Native Hawaiians (6), to enforce discriminatory healthcare policies in the name of American patriotism and the squandering of Hawaiian nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last aspect to look at is the constant land desecration that Hawai’i suffers from. From the arrival of Europeans to now, Hawaiian land is constantly used for other means, though Native Hawaiians see it as sacred. For example, in 1988, approximately 1,100 ancestral Native Hawaiian remains were removed for the construction of the Ritz-Carlton Hotel, on Maui, Hawai’i (7). The constant land desecration continues today, and a more recent example would be the Thirty Metre Telescope (TMT), which is being built on Mauna Kea, a sacred volcano to Native Hawaiins (8). Though many Hawaiians do in fact support the TMT on Mauna Kea, with Hawai’i’s Supreme Court ruling that the construction permit was valid, many others oppose it because they believe sacred land is being harmed (8), and arguably because it takes away the remaining agency that Hawaiians have left. Though telescopes are already on the Mauna Kea, an issue that some activists have is that, “they keep asking for more and more and more, and we have no say at this point” (9), upholding the earlier point that this also concerns the agency of Native Hawaiians and their land, not an opposition to a telescope itself. For others, it is also about the resources that Hawai’i continues to lose, as Hawai’i has a “precious and fragile ecology” (9), so such a large construction project on the Mauna Kea is harmful for the remaining resources of the Kingdom. The land desecration that Hawai’i continues to face, whether in the name of science or not, are arguably a product of U.S. occupation on Indigenous land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. occupation of Hawai’i started with an act of war launched to overthrow the Hawaiian monarchy and is now under the full acknowledgement of the United Nations as an occupation. To this day, Native Hawaiians are subject to the changes in their education and healthcare infrastructures, as well as routine land desecration. Under international law, the United States holds an illegal occupation of Hawai’i (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hunt, Tam. “What is the status of Hawaii under international law today?” Interview with Prof. Keanu Sai. Tam Hunt, August 27, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://tamhunt.medium.com/what-is-the-status-of-hawaii-under-international-law-today-863349e678e1&quot;&gt;https://tamhunt.medium.com/what-is-the-status-of-hawaii-under-international-law-today-863349e678e1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smithsonian.com. “Hawaii – History and Heritage.” Smithsonian Magazine, November 6, 2007. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/hawaii-history-and-heritage-4164590/&quot;&gt;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/travel/hawaii-history-and-heritage-4164590/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sai, Keanu. “The Illegal Overthrow of the Hawaiian Kingdom Government.” National Education Association, April 4, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/illegal-overthrow-hawaiian-kingdom-government&quot;&gt;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/illegal-overthrow-hawaiian-kingdom-government&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Learning Network. “Hawaiian Monarchy Overthrown by America-Backed Bussinessmen.” The New York Times, January 17, 2012. &lt;a href=&quot;https://learning.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/17/jan-17-1893-hawaiian-monarchy-overthrown-by-america-backed-businessmen/&quot;&gt;https://learning.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/17/jan-17-1893-hawaiian-monarchy-overthrown-by-america-backed-businessmen/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sai, Keanu. “The U.S. Occupation of the Hawaiian Kingdom.” National Education Association, October 1, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/us-occupation-hawaiian-kingdom&quot;&gt;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/us-occupation-hawaiian-kingdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sai, Keanu. “The Impact of the U.S. Occupation on the Hawaiian People.” National Education Association, October 13, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/impact-us-occupation-hawaiian-people&quot;&gt;https://www.nea.org/advocating-for-change/new-from-nea/impact-us-occupation-hawaiian-people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Halealoha, Edward Avao. “Native Burials, Human Rights and Sacred Bones.” Cultural Survival, March 2000. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.culturalsurvival.org/publications/cultural-survival-quarterly/native-burials-human-rights-and-sacred-bones&quot;&gt;https://www.culturalsurvival.org/publications/cultural-survival-quarterly/native-burials-human-rights-and-sacred-bones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Witze, Alexandra. “Astronomy impasse: What’s next for the Thirty Meter Telescope?” Nature, August 7, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02354-5&quot;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-02354-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cuddy, Alice. “Hawaii TMT: Desecrating sacred land or finding new frontiers” BBC, July 25, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-49082156&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-49082156&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marhamah Sohail&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How the Law Hurts - An Investigation into the Indian Farmers]]></title><description><![CDATA[In September 2020, the President of India, Ram Nath Novind, approved three bills that were passed by Parliament a few weeks prior…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/e6e7b/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMCBAX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAv/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABUylOKcZ4P//EABoQAQACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAwAREkL/2gAIAQEAAQUCLdSLHXUnLpcnlkj/AP/EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEf/aAAgBAwEBPwGNj//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREv/aAAgBAgEBPwGMv//EABsQAAEEAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECECExABES/9oACAEBAAY/AlAunmNzlU3/xAAeEAACAgEFAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAhQTFRYXGBkf/aAAgBAQABPyG/Bqg5YnzmYJ+qUcwsc3GMTLXeEwb7n//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQNC//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEEH/2gAIAQMBAT8QRsP/xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABACH/2gAIAQIBAT8QXqTP/8QAHRABAAICAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBYXGB0f/aAAgBAQABPxBlj7dqQ8iguVtuKVT1jjuFxYBrK1/WWg8q9qaeD9gYdUfArHEM+7cf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Farmer&amp;#39;s protesting their rights&quot;
        title=&quot;Farmer&amp;#39;s protesting their rights&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/828fb/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/ff44c/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg 158w,
/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/a6688/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg 315w,
/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/828fb/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg 630w,
/static/931b0747efd1ec767689728047e74606/e6e7b/how-the-law-hurts-an-investigation-into-the-indian-farmers.jpg 770w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2020, the President of India, Ram Nath Novind, approved three bills that were passed by Parliament a few weeks prior, essentially turning them into laws (1). Since then, nationwide farmers’ protests have taken place in opposition of these laws, as many believe that they cause harm to farmers. Even in Canada, protests have taken place in British Colombia and Winnipeg, with the slogan “No Farmers, No Food” (2), which can also be seen in many pictures throughout Indian-wide protests. Passing these laws have been a controversial choice by the Indian government, with opposition from many perspectives, but how exactly did we get here? What is it about these laws that the farmers see as harmful? To answer these questions, we must first look at the laws themselves, and try to understand them. For the purposes of this article, the laws will be referred to as bills henceforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first bill, the Farmers Produce Trade and Commerce Bill, is designed so that farmers can go directly to companies to sell their produce (1). This, in turn, allows companies to set their own prices and deal with the legality beforehand. However, a key concern is that 82% of farmers are small farmers – they have less than 5 hectares of land – so big businesses can take advantage of them (1). Being a small farmer under this law means that there is no guaranteed protection if they are not satisfied with the price of their produce or feel that the legal issues cause harm to them, as many cannot afford to go to court against massive supermarket chains (1). This law begs the question of protection; how can farmers be protected when they are open to exploitation in the agricultural market, if everything is decided beforehand without their essential input? How can farmers be guaranteed an adequate price for their labor and produce?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bill, the Farmer (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Prices and Farm Services Bill is designed so that state governments can set up Agricultural Produce Market Committees (ACMPs), allowing them to set up markets throughout the state (1). The goal of this is to provide farmers with the opportunity to do business with firms for future years at an agreed price, while also transferring market unpredictability to the sponsors (1). This law, however, also allows farmers to sell their produce outside of the ACMP marketplaces, so they can now sell anywhere, even online (1). However, a problem that arises from this is that outside of ACMP marketplaces, farmers are not guaranteed their usual Minimum Support Price, which once acted like a safety net, by giving a promised price that cannot be altered (3). This price was usually an exploitative amount (1), and the removal of it in other marketplaces can be seen as even more exploitative for the farmers selling their produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third bill, the Essential Commodities Bill, is an amendment from 1955, when it was first brought in (1). This is arguably the most controversial bill, as it seeks to control production all the way to distribution of certain products that are deemed essential, with the idea being that stores cannot hoard these items for future use (1). However, with the 2020 Amendment, certain items like cereals, onions, and potatoes are removed from essential products, meaning that stores can hoard them for future sales (1). Furthermore, this Amendment also removes government power from enforcing hoarding or stockholding limits (1). The problem, then, is that this means that stores can hoard and artificially increase prices if they wish, causing problems for poorer people who rely on these food products, that they would not be able to afford henceforth (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Seventh Schedule within the Indian Constitution is cause for the legal controversy around these agricultural laws (4). Within it, there are three lists where power is distributed between the Centre and the states (4). There is the Union List, which is under Parliament’s jurisdiction exclusively, the State List, under state jurisdiction exclusively, and the Concurrent List, under both Parliament and State jurisdiction, allowing both powers to legislate (4). Parliamentary law triumphs when there is conflict (4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agriculture comes under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution (5). Under the Concurrent List, Entry 33 is what the Central Government used to bring enact these laws (5). Entry 33 was amended in 1955 to bring in more products (5), with its current form reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“33. Trade and commerce in, and the production, supply and distribution of,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The products of any industry where the control of such industry by the Union is declared by Parliament by law to be expedient in the public interest, and important goods of the same kinds such as products;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foodstuffs, including edible oil seeds and oils;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cattle fodder, including oilcakes and other concentrates;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw cotton whether ginned or unginned, and cotton seeds; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw jute” (6).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, Entry 33 under the Seventh Schedule, which is under the Concurrent List, has an amendment history associated with it. With the amendment in 1955, points (b) and (e) were introduced to Entry 33 (5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bills that were passed have a new interpretation of the law, and as Amit Jaiswal writes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Union government has tried to it as a standalone provision and it conveniently ignored the context, object, and historical background of the sub-entries (5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the first bill, the Central Government also seeks to control sales within states, though agriculture largely falls under state government jurisdiction (5). In their current form, the two first Bills do not fall under Constitutional law, as per Entry 33. This is a controversial topic, as there are people in support of the bills, and people who oppose them in light of the Seventh Schedule. Farmers see them as exploitative and have gone to massive protests in opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since November 2020, thousands of farmers are protesting these controversial bills (7). Between September to February, talks between the government and farmers unions have taken place, with no set solution as of yet (7). Though we have outlined the legal concerns, the farmers’ concerns revolve around being vulnerable to the free market, and the end of wholesale markets and fixed prices (ie. The Minimum Support Price) (7). As such, massive protests have broken out, and the January 26th protests are set to be the longest in world history (8). If so much controversy comes with these laws, we can then ask what the government has done to amend them, or to repeal them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January, the Indian government offered to suspend the Farm Laws for 18 months, but the farmers rejected them (9). The exploitation that the farmers currently face is not going to go away with the suspension of these laws. The openness to the free market that the farmers believe will leave them susceptible to exploitation by big businesses and supermarket chains will not end with an 18-month suspension, creating the possibility for this to happen again, perhaps even turning into a cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plight of the Indian farmers, however, did not start in 2020 with the introduction of these new bills. In fact, the suicide rate of the farmers accounts for 10% of all suicides in the country, with over 12,000 farmer suicides reported every year since 2013 (10). There is no one set reason that causes the high suicide rates, but rather, it stems from many areas, such as input costs like equipment and chemical costs, the distress caused by loans, and even a water crisis (10). When understanding the way these laws can be exploitative to the farmers by giving them no fallback and no guarantees of protection and coupling this with the low literacy rate that stops farmers from seeking out full governmental policies (10), one can see how these laws pave the way for a heightened farmers crisis, manifesting through suicide. The concern for India’s farmers is not just concentrated to India but must be sought globally, for both the protection of farmers’ livelihoods, and their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a global context, Simran Jeet Singh says that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;essential workers across the world are suffering. The farmers in India represent all of them, and their resistance to unjust legislation that privileges the uber-wealthy corporations is a resistance that speaks to so many of us all over the world (11)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exploitation these farmers face by large market players, global attention and awareness must be mobilized in their support. However, not all of us can relate, because not all of us are essential workers. Instead, we benefit from the Indian farmers daily. India is the world’s largest exporters of spices, exporting 68% (11). The country is also largest exporter of Basmati rice and milk producer (11). When so much of what we have comes from the Indian farmers, down to some of the clothing we wear, there is just cause to mobilize to support them, through organizations like Khalsa Aid, or simply raising awareness. The farmers crisis is one that speaks to all of us, either as essential workers, or as everyday people, because we owe them so much. Leaving them to market susceptibility with no way out will only make this crisis worse, and an 18-month suspension of these laws will not help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Standard, “What are the Farm Bills,” Business Standard, 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/about/what-is-farm-bills#collapse&quot;&gt;https://www.business-standard.com/about/what-is-farm-bills#collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samantha Beattie. “Why Are Canadians Rallying Behind Farmers Protesting In India?,” Huffington Post, December 10, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/tools_citationguide/citation-guide-1.html&quot;&gt;https://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/tools_citationguide/citation-guide-1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;India Today Web Desk. “Explained: What is MSP and why farmers are protesting over it?,” India Today, September 29, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/explained-what-is-msp-and-why-farmers-are-protesting-over-it-1726658-2020-09-29&quot;&gt;https://www.indiatoday.in/india/story/explained-what-is-msp-and-why-farmers-are-protesting-over-it-1726658-2020-09-29&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faizan Mustafa. “An Expert Explains: The arguments for and against the three central farm laws,” The Indian Express, September 29, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/an-expert-explains-farm-acts-and-federalism-6622769/&quot;&gt;https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/an-expert-explains-farm-acts-and-federalism-6622769/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amit Jaiswal. “What Will the Legal Challenge to the Modi Government’s Farm Bills Look Like?,” The Wire, October 5, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewire.in/law/farm-bills-legal-challenge-constitution-seventh-schedule-supreme-court&quot;&gt;https://thewire.in/law/farm-bills-legal-challenge-constitution-seventh-schedule-supreme-court&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legislative Department. “THE CONSTITUTION (THIRD AMENDMENT) ACT, 1954,” Government of India, Ministry of Law and Justice, n.d., &lt;a href=&quot;https://legislative.gov.in/constitution-third-amendment-act-1954&quot;&gt;https://legislative.gov.in/constitution-third-amendment-act-1954&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BBC. “Farm laws: Are India’s new reforms a ‘death warrant’ for farmers?,” BBC News, February 16, 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-54233080&quot;&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-54233080&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chris Zukowsky. “World’s Largest Protest Creating the History Farmer’s Protest in India,” CUPW VANCOUVER, January 26, 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cupwvancouver.org/worlds-largest-protest-creating-the-history-farmers-protest-in-india/&quot;&gt;https://www.cupwvancouver.org/worlds-largest-protest-creating-the-history-farmers-protest-in-india/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Al Jazeera. “Indian farmers reject government’s offer to suspend new laws,” Al Jazeera, January 22, 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/1/22/indian-farmers-reject-governments-offer-to-suspend-new-laws&quot;&gt;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2021/1/22/indian-farmers-reject-governments-offer-to-suspend-new-laws&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clear IAS Team. “Farmers’ Suicides in India – Reasons and Responses,” Clear IAS, January 6, 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clearias.com/farmers-suicides/&quot;&gt;https://www.clearias.com/farmers-suicides/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alisha Ebrahimji. “Thousands of people are protesting with farmers in India. This is why you should care,” CNN, December 11, 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/12/11/world/farmer-protests-india-protests-hnk-trnd/index.html&quot;&gt;https://www.cnn.com/2020/12/11/world/farmer-protests-india-protests-hnk-trnd/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marhamah Sohail&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unreliable and Biased Eyewitness Testimonies]]></title><description><![CDATA[Did you know eyewitness testimonies are not necessarily as reliable as they perceived to be? In fact, even the most honest individuals are…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/72e01/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 75.31645569620254%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAUBAwT/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABm1CDvFwX/8QAGxAAAgMAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDERICE0L/2gAIAQEAAQUCU2Dv4jlTfnVFn//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AYj/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAYEAACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAICExcf/aAAgBAQAGPwKcWj//xAAcEAEAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMUFRcbH/2gAIAQEAAT8hRINNvZxDiohy7l0nuoJVUQ5+p//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQqP8A/8QAFxEBAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEhMf/aAAgBAwEBPxCuoP/EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQEf/aAAgBAgEBPxBdn//EABsQAQEAAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExUXFB/9oACAEBAAE/ENW/lBCLL5kFXSQVhjD0OMRsavGIlp0tuL0B+xGf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        title=&quot;Prelaw Shadowers&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/828fb/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/ff44c/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg 158w,
/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/a6688/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg 315w,
/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/828fb/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg 630w,
/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/0ede0/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg 945w,
/static/92d1f6e6a69709c8b8ce570c91452b29/72e01/unreliable-and-biased-eyewitness-testimonies.jpg 1024w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know eyewitness testimonies are not necessarily as reliable as they perceived to be? In fact, even the most honest individuals are prone to make wrongful convictions through their testimonies. So, what makes these eyewitness testimonies unreliable even though most individuals believe they constitute solid evidence for criminal cases? Research supports this idea that eyewitness testimonies can be unreliable due to the cross-race effect, especially when it comes to racial and ethnic populations. According to Innocence Canada, the cross-race effect increases the unreliability of eyewitness testimony (1). Studies have demonstrated that an individual is 1.4 times more likely to recognize and correctly identify a person’s face within the same race as the individual in contrast to a face from another racial group (1). The cross-race effect within legal procedures impacts the way individuals perceive specific categories of individuals, which can be detrimental towards innocent and vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minorities are overrepresented in the Canadian justice system as defendants in judicial proceedings and as inmates in prisons due to the perceived notion of others. The common misconception is that individuals believe eyewitness memories are a reliable source of evidence and jurors tend to believe in confident eyewitnesses against the immigrant population. However, the relationship between confidence and accuracy of eyewitness testimonies is weakly established in research and an unreliable source of information. The most prominent factor that impacts the storage and retrieval of eyewitness memory is the personal biases and the eyewitness’s perception of the defendant. Further, cross-racial identification becomes harder for individuals to do than identification within their own race due to these biases, which leads to inaccurate eyewitness testimonies and innocent people in prisons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cross-race effect is seen in cases where eyewitness testimonies are difficult to take into account due to the inability to recognize other multi-ethnic individuals. According to Kask and Rundu, similar race faces are more precisely perceived than other-race faces (2). By analyzing the impacts of recognizing similar and different race faces when diverse ethnic groups are introduced to the individuals together, the study looks at the effect of generic knowledge on recognizing other-race faces (2). Through photographs of similar and different race faces with stereotypical names, the researchers found similar race faces were better perceived in the target-present lineup and more accurately dismissed in the target-present lineup than different race faces names (2). Their findings suggest that recognizing multi-ethnicity perpetrators is a difficult and problematic operation, which is more susceptible to false and biased eyewitness testimonies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the recognition bias is prominent among many racial groups, evidence suggests the effect is most profound for white individuals perceiving other members of racial minority groups. Johnson and Fredrickson believe Caucasian participants perceive Black and White faces differently compared to other racial groups (3). Through a recognition task, the researchers suggest that the differences between the recognition of own-race and cross-race faces produce cross-race faces as less holistically than own-race faces (3). They found that the facial recognition in the brain and the participant focus on racial cues produces an effect on cross-race faces (3). This recognition and attitude towards other racial groups are due to White individuals reflecting a cultural environment that is discriminatory and prejudiced towards other individuals outside their own racial category. In another study, Walker and Hewstone found racial biases being significant in White and South Asian individuals when determining own versus other-race faces, which provides an advantage for perceptually determining their own race (4). Through classifying morphed face stimuli into different categories, they found both White and South Asian groups were better at viewing their own-race faces in comparison to other-race faces (4). The results reveal underlying racial biases as White participants displayed anti-other race bias through questionnaires (4). This biasing effect creates cross-racial eyewitness identifications as highly unreliable and appalling consequences for the criminal justice system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, the perceptions of eyewitness confidence explain why mistaken eyewitness identifications contribute to wrongful convictions. Dodson and Dobolyi examine the cross-race effect and the effect of confidence ratings in eyewitness identifications (5). Participants encountered same-race and cross-race faces, which they had to identify during line-up recognition tests (5). The researchers found better accuracy and confidence when participants observed same-race faces in contrast to cross-race individuals and more confidence when individuals choose from line-up than not present (5). Participants were also overconfident when choosing cross-race faces over same-race faces, which reveals the vulnerability of mistaken eyewitnesses producing more false convictions for cross-race individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eyewitness testimony can be subject to unconscious memory distortions and biases even among the most confident witness testimonies. The existing research emphasizes that human memory is inclined to be fallible and susceptible to error, which impacts an individual’s eyewitness identification. In particular, white individuals perceive faces of their own ethnic group as more recognizable compared to faces of other ethnic categories by attributing bias associations and overconfidence to cross-racial faces. These biases pertaining to individuals’ ability to better recognize their own racial group, in turn, create false eyewitness testimonies. These factors make it even more difficult for convicted racial individuals to defend their case due to biased eyewitness identifications, which produces wrongful convictions. It is essential to understand the consequences of unreliable eyewitness testimonies to shine light on the ineffectiveness of legal safeguards that are supposed to protect mistakenly identified convicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Causes of Wrongful Convictions, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.innocencecanada.com/causes-of-wrongful-convictions/&quot;&gt;https://www.innocencecanada.com/causes-of-wrongful-convictions/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kask, Kristjan, and Rundu, Kaarel. “The Effects of Presentation Methods and Semantic Information on Multi-ethnicity Face Recognition.” The European Journal of Psychology Applied to Legal Context 4, no. 1 (2012): 43-57. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/10683160802131131&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/10683160802131131&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Johnson, J. Kareem, and Fredrickson, L. Barbara. “We All Look the Same to Me”: Positive Emotions Eliminate the Own-Race in Face Recognition.” Psychological Science 16, no. 11, (2005): 875–881. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2005.01631.x&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2005.01631.x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walker, M. Pamela, and Hewstone, Miles. “The Influence of Social Factors and Implicit Racial Bias on a Generalized Own-Race Effect.” Applied Cognitive Psychology 22, no. 4, (2008): 441–453. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.1382&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.1382&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dodson, S. Chad, and Dobolyi, G. Dobolyi. “Confidence and Eyewitness Identifications: The Cross‐Race Effect, Decision Time and Accuracy.” Applied Cognitive Psychology 30, (2016): 113– 125. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.3178&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/acp.3178&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharuka Sivanandam&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dealing with Imposter Syndrome]]></title><description><![CDATA[Have you ever felt like you do not measure up to those around you? Or like you are not good enough to be in the career you chose? You may be…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/0fa73/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQFA//EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAG0gxjDpHE//8QAGhAAAwEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIDABIUI//aAAgBAQABBQJiFWFebYek5wEZ9phv/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABH/2gAIAQMBAT8BV//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAR/9oACAECAQE/AYf/xAAdEAACAgEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhAhAiMUKh/9oACAEBAAY/Ank+ETe7zS+yGkyIR//EABwQAQACAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAETFRECFBcf/aAAgBAQABPyHCiWzIWJ680+cWcRVGIitbu0joqf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQrz//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARAAH/2gAIAQMBAT8QTIX/xAAXEQEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREh/9oACAECAQE/ENSp/8QAGhABAAMBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFRcf/aAAgBAQABPxBTEWwXhHs3d6G8vwMUdNjIRqDgSKWWO8CpThqdtn//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/828fb/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/ff44c/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 158w,
/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/a6688/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 315w,
/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/828fb/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 630w,
/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/0ede0/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 945w,
/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/3ac88/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 1260w,
/static/920ca52f0eea4a042316acbfbb66f9bf/0fa73/dealing-with-imposter-syndrome.jpg 6105w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you do not measure up to those around you? Or like you are not good enough to be in the career you chose? You may be experiencing imposter syndrome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imposter syndrome, as defined by Oxford dictionary describes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the persistent inability to believe that one’s success is deserved or has been legitimately achieved as a result of one’s efforts or skills (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently became aware of imposter syndrome while talking to my peers who have had experience with it. Although it sounds like something out of the game Among Us, it is a very real and damaging thing to experience, especially when applying to law school and within the legal field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When imposter syndrome takes over, any achievement is viewed as good luck or timing. You constantly doubt your accomplishments and feel as if you do not deserve them (1). If you have ever experienced imposter syndrome, you know how difficult it can be to grapple with the anxiety of not feeling good enough when applying to earn your JD. According to Professor Amanda Peters from South Texas College of Law, some students admitted they put off applying to law school because of their perceived weaknesses, believed their undergraduate grades or law school acceptances were mistakes or believed they would be unable to keep up with the fast-paced environment in law school. (2) The LSAT and applying to law school, in general, is a very daunting process. When it comes to preparing, the types of questions, and how your score impacts your future, imposter syndrome is sometimes inevitable (1). The score you receive on the LSAT can be seen as a make or break for your job placement after graduation and, most of all, your chances of getting into a good law school. This increasing pressure of how good your score needs to be accompanied by overwhelming feelings that you will never be good enough is a significant factor influencing imposter syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law students and those applying to law school are particularly susceptible to experiencing imposter syndrome (2). While applying to law school, you are constantly competing to have the best application and have the best LSAT score to get into the best law school, but it does not stop there. Even in law school, students constantly compare themselves to one another as they are ranked against their peers (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Peters, imposter syndrome &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is causing some very promising students to shoot themselves in the foot before they even had a chance to succeed (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, many students have fallen prey to the feelings of not being good enough and are unconsciously hindering their opportunities to reach their full potential. Some students never make it past the first year of law school because they give in to the feelings of self-doubt that imposter syndrome pushes onto us (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we overcome this? How do we make ourselves bigger than this phenomenon in order to succeed? The first step is recognizing you have a problem and realizing that others are probably feeling the same way you do (3). It is also essential to pay attention to your thoughts and self-talk. In other words, try to train your brain to mostly think of motivating and uplifting thoughts primarily, and if you feel yourself falling into a spiral of negativity, change the script (3). Instead of telling yourself you do not belong, start thinking of what you bring to the table. In other words, what are the strengths that make you suitable for applying to law school and becoming a law student? Recognizing your strength also provides room for a healthy version of self-growth and realizing your limitations (3). We all have limits, which should not be misconstrued as reasons why you are not suitable for a particular career. Some may even say when you look at imposter syndrome, it can be seen as a healthy recognition of one’s limitations. It is a natural and common feature of being a professional (3). Lastly, and what I think is the most important out of all these steps, is to talk to someone you trust about how you are feeling. In talking to someone, you can help work out what you are feeling, discover that you are not alone and build new relationships that will be there for support in the future (3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think imposter syndrome is an important topic to be discussed, especially for individuals like me who were unaware of it. Going forward, I know I will be aware of my feelings when applying to law school and try my best not to let myself fall into a wave of negativity. As long as we can recognize that we are not alone when experiencing things like this, we can work to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stetson Law. How to Deal With Impostor Syndrome When Applying to Law School. Stetson Law, January 3, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://lawblog.law.stetson.edu/how-to-deal-with-imposter-syndrome-when-applying-to-law-school&quot;&gt;https://lawblog.law.stetson.edu/how-to-deal-with-imposter-syndrome-when-applying-to-law-school&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peters, Amanda. “Discussing Imposter Syndrome.” Teach Law Better, September 9, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://teachlawbetter.com/2020/09/09/discussing-imposter-syndrome/&quot;&gt;https://teachlawbetter.com/2020/09/09/discussing-imposter-syndrome/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;March, Courtney. “Recognizing the Reality of Imposter Syndrome.” Canadian Lawyer. Canadian Lawyer, July 31, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canadianlawyermag.com/news/opinion/recognizing-the-reality-of-imposter-syndrome/270562&quot;&gt;https://www.canadianlawyermag.com/news/opinion/recognizing-the-reality-of-imposter-syndrome/270562&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anjali Kupchand&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Racist Undertones and the Secrecy of Law Firms on Bay Street]]></title><description><![CDATA[Although conversations surrounding diversity and the participation of black people in the legal field have increased over the years…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/f3ac8/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.45569620253164%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQDBf/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAED/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAFD0ppU2QA//8QAGhAAAwADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIDABESMf/aAAgBAQABBQKvih9Cx0bdNVnfFGf/xAAXEQEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARES/9oACAEDAQE/Acyp/8QAFxEBAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEREv/aAAgBAgEBPwHcLf/EABsQAAIDAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAhEhECKB/9oACAEBAAY/AsMjKxXjF1VmzfnH/8QAGxABAAMBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBUXH/2gAIAQEAAT8hvblTzMgSr22EBRaNEivrHHtQaqXzEuH99n//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEJs//8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQD/2gAIAQMBAT8QWif/xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABH/2gAIAQIBAT8QAJO3/8QAGxABAQADAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAIUGBkaH/2gAIAQEAAT8QdJQJdKeHbMdmFEDNaX3glAKgmsMYREvgwSawdA+YVasRdnmf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/828fb/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/ff44c/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 158w,
/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/a6688/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 315w,
/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/828fb/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 630w,
/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/0ede0/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 945w,
/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/3ac88/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 1260w,
/static/04de43db56bcbf8280f29cd77417f50b/f3ac8/racist-undertones-and-the-secrecy-of-law-firms-on-bay-street.jpg 5761w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although conversations surrounding diversity and the participation of black people in the legal field have increased over the years, especially with the Black Lives Matter movement, law firms continue to possess racist sentiments. Blind to the overrepresentation of white people, firms and corporations take pride in circulating pamphlets and publicly advertising their love and passion for diversity. However, every person of color who has been given the chance to work on Bay Street has something to say about the racist environment and dealing with problems which the overwhelmingly white population does not face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous legal professionals within Ontario have stepped forward, sharing their stories of struggling to relate to their co-workers in law firms given the drastic differences between respective backgrounds and experiences. The issue presents itself through multiple avenues including social settings in which Black people tend to be blatantly excluded, especially in colleague gatherings such as after work drinks which are specifically designed to build a sense of community. Social affairs of that nature are essential for the expansion of one’s network while fostering healthy friendships yet people of color gain nothing from them (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social assimilation of Black people in the corporate world is further hindered through the illegitimate yet increasing use of nepotism. The inequitable practice enables favouritism and allows the powerful and mostly white legal professionals to give an unfair preference to their own white family members or friends, during the process of recruitment. The complete disregard of other eligible and worthy candidates, simply to maintain connections or return family favors, limits the chances of Black people gaining access to prestigious law firms on Bay Street (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2017, University of Toronto law school graduate Hadiya Roderique realized that the big law firms on Bay Street pay very little attention to merit, proving how the North American dream is exactly that. A dream, rather than a reality (3). It is scientifically proven that humans tend to surround themselves with individuals similar to them, who in turn validate their choices and actions. To some extent, this explains why white people continue to dominate big firms, as they hire people who physically look just like them. To further illustrate the issue, a survey conducted by the Law Society of Ontario in 2014 revealed that 57% of racialized people believe that having different cultural backgrounds is a career disadvantage (5). Although a few firms are aware of their lack of diversity, their attempts to employ people of color falls short due to a fundamentally flawed system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hadiya put it best in her bombshell essay published by the Globe and Mail when she said &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They hire people who fit into the firm as it already exists (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a response, the President of the Canadian Bar Association acknowledged the barriers faced by people of color by stating that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;systemic discrimination is unfortunately baked into the system&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;adding on that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you have to fight pretty hard to defy the odds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in order to make it (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Society and its institutions have become fixed in their discriminatory views, allowing little to no flexibility for change to take place. These unfair and unyielding practices have normalized people of color to work much harder in order to be offered the same opportunities as their white counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, multiple Black legal professionals have come forward in exposing big law firms, revealing their true colors, by sharing stories of implicit and explicit racism they faced on a daily basis. The prejudice is evident even through small acts including, being falsely assumed for an assistant rather than a lawyer, repeatedly ignored, talked over in meetings and participating in uncomfortable and rather inappropriate conversations focused on their physical appearance which includes, but is not limited to, their hair and clothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employers do their best in concealing their blatant racism which is evident through their refusal to engage in operations aimed at tackling their biases. A prime of example of this includes the collection of data to investigate the exact levels of diversity and eventually make the information accessible to the public. The Globe and Mail stepped forward by reaching out to twenty different law firms and asked their employees to answer survey questions in the hopes of taking a step closer to the truth. Out of the twenty firms, it has been reported that only about half of them provided the information, with only a few willing to share the findings. The others were insisting on maintaining complete privacy and denied their participation in the survey. Six firms including Osler, Bennet Jones, Davies, McMillian, Blaney McMurtry and Folger Rubinoff, all declined the sharing of the findings of the investigation to the public, with WeirFoulds blatantly declining to answer any questions (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McCarthy Tretault happened to be the only law firm confident enough to be completely transparent with the survey, alongside Fasken, Goodmans, Dentons and Aird &amp;#x26; Berlis who were also fairly open. The CEO of Tretault, Dave Leonard, admitted that around 2% of the lawyers, partners and articling students at the firm identified as Black, confessing how he was not proud about the levels of diversity (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other companies which choose to stay silent and brush their shortcomings under the rug, Dave Leonard decided to share it anyways and claimed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;transparency is part of how we’re going to solve this.
He acknowledged his own position of privilege when he commented
I do recognize that I’m here because of hard work and intelligence and all the rest of it. But I’m also here because of my role and my place in society, and where I grew up and how I grew up and how I grew up and the colour of my skin and my gender (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is there a dire need for more transparency at the hands of law firms, but effort also needs to be made to ensure that Black lawyers feel safe enough to share their valuable stories regarding discrimination. Bay Street is relatively small; therefore individuals refrain from sharing their experiences in fear of being blacklisted, labelled as disloyal and being subjected to critical remarks which are to follow inevitably (3). The reputation of entry level lawyers depends on the biased opinions of upper-class white men who want their employees to be obedient and submissive. Unfortunately, speaking one’s truth or advocating for change actively obstructs the advancement of an individual’s career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spirits of bright lawyers from various backgrounds continue to crush due to the consistent forms of prejudice and the lack of acceptance they face in big law firms. To address the problem, a thorough investigation needs to be conducted looking into the biggest law firms in Ontario. When people are presented real statistics and numbers, they are bound to take the matter more seriously since the information is available to the public and not something that can be easily dismissed. The publishing of such reports would also allow Black lawyers to feel more comfortable in sharing their personal experiences through major news outlets like Hadiya Roderique, without the constant fear of being targeted. All in all, encouraging open discussions of such a pressing issue and giving Black lawyers a voice is the very first step in tackling the discriminatory system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anne Gaviola. “First-hand accounts of what racism looks like in Corporate Canada.” BNN Bloomberg, October 5, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bnnbloomberg.ca/first-hand-accounts-of-what-racism-looks-like-in-corporate-canada-1.1501573&quot;&gt;https://www.bnnbloomberg.ca/first-hand-accounts-of-what-racism-looks-like-in-corporate-canada-1.1501573&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christine Dobby, “Why are there still so few Black lawyers on Bay Street?” The Globe and Mail, July 17, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-why-are-there-still-so-few-black-lawyers-on-bay-street/&quot;&gt;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-why-are-there-still-so-few-black-lawyers-on-bay-street/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hadiya Roderique, “Black on Bay Street: Hadiya Roderique had it all. But still could not fit in.” The Globe and Mail, November 4, 2017. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/toronto/hadiya-roderique-black-on-bay-street/article36823806/&quot;&gt;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/toronto/hadiya-roderique-black-on-bay-street/article36823806/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Star Staff, “3.2 per cent of Ontario’s lawyers are Black. Why that’s a problem for law and society.” Toronto Star, August 31, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thestar.com/podcasts/thismatters/2020/08/31/35-per-cent-of-ontarios-lawyers-are-black-why-thats-a-problem-for-law-and-society.html#:~:text=The%20Law%20Society%20of%20Ontario,of%20Ontario&amp;#x27;s%20lawyers%20are%20Black&quot;&gt;https://www.thestar.com/podcasts/thismatters/2020/08/31/35-per-cent-of-ontarios-lawyers-are-black-why-thats-a-problem-for-law-and-society.html#:~:text=The%20Law%20Society%20of%20Ontario,of%20Ontario’s%20lawyers%20are%20Black&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veronica Appia, “Why are there so few Black lawyers in Ontario?” Toronto.com &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.toronto.com/news-story/10128115-analysis-why-are-there-so-few-black-lawyers-in-ontario-/&quot;&gt;https://www.toronto.com/news-story/10128115-analysis-why-are-there-so-few-black-lawyers-in-ontario-/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myra Mansoor&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Transition from University to 1L]]></title><description><![CDATA[The transition from studying at university to attending first year of law school tends to take a massive toll on people’s lifestyle and…]]></description><link>https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-transition-from-university-to-1L/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://prelawshadowers.com/blog/the-transition-from-university-to-1L/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 630px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/40a4d/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 71.51898734177216%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAOABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAUBAgT/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAai2Q94tLP/EABgQAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACERMB/9oACAEBAAEFAovTiKRLoaGh/8QAFhEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIR/9oACAEDAQE/AYpFP//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAh/9oACAECAQE/Aar/xAAeEAABAgcBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAITEBAgMQERJygf/aAAgBAQAGPwJJtfBamYc2YYY//8QAGhABAQADAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARIVFBof/aAAgBAQABPyF+kbREw8NJyDwcD0gkaa//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEGDv/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAGH/2gAIAQMBAT8QFH//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEVH/2gAIAQIBAT8QrcP/xAAbEAEBAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAxIUGBUf/aAAgBAQABPxBJDHEAvxxWNblXpg17Sqv2cEvfUw6BL1kGPI3zn//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        title=&quot;Lawyer at their desk&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/828fb/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/ff44c/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 158w,
/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/a6688/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 315w,
/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/828fb/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 630w,
/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/0ede0/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 945w,
/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/3ac88/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 1260w,
/static/5bbf737282fa8fb56140fef3c2de8ff3/40a4d/the-transition-from-university-to-1L.jpg 2889w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transition from studying at university to attending first year of law school tends to take a massive toll on people’s lifestyle and mental health. Although some students might take pride in their ability to manage their time and workload efficiently, the pressure of law school is completely different from the type one faces in university (4). The drastic change can cause a lot of people discontinue the law journey due to their inability to cope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, pursuing higher education comes with the increase of ‘workaholic’ culture, in which people forget to prioritize self-care and work themselves too hard (5). The culture may start when individuals are still in university since students are already subjected to the immeasurable stress of studying for the LSAT, ensuring they have a GPA which stands out, working on their applications and applying to various law schools. However, stress levels spike once a person finally begins attending law school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The teaching method is different from other educational institutions. Most professors use the Socratic method in which a person is picked from a crowd of students and asked rapid fire questions (7). This technique tends to be intimidating since an individual is much more vulnerable in front of an audience, as opposed to writing a test in an examination hall. It is much more aggressive and has been one of the reasons why a lot of law students feel on edge and incredibly stressed (7). An individual’s mental health can deteriorate due to the constant elevated stress levels, which can lead to anxiety, depression, or other mental health disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Socratic method of teaching makes concepts a lot more difficult to grasp since students have been conditioned to study differently in earlier stages of their academic career. In university, people are tested through their ability to memorise general concepts and apply critical thinking skills to form solutions. Contrastingly, law schools utilize didactic teaching methods, where memorization plays an insignificant role (2). The Socratic method is commonly used by law professors to engage with students by having one on one conversations to test their knowledge. It requires one to obtain extensive knowledge on certain topics while possessing a logical and practical understanding of complex situations. Since they are unfamiliar with the teaching method, first year law students can feel overwhelmed by having to figure out their new technique of studying and simultaneously being bombarded with more work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing relationships outside of school also becomes a major challenge faced by students going into law school. Friends, family members, and partners may feel ignored or neglected since students do not possessive a lot of free time dedicated towards managing their social life (1). Law schools are notorious in creating unmatched levels of stress for their students, which can leave them and the members of their social circle, feeling lonely. For parents, it may seem like their children have no interest in taking time out for them, even though in reality students are simply battling the stress of school. Professor Lydia Bleasdale from University of Leeds found that law students have very little free time to pursue relationships and even activities unrelated to the profession, unlike their cohorts. In fact, most activities which law students engage in outside of studying, is likely to be connected to the field of law (5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason why law school comes with its own level of stress is the way students are not given a lot of opportunities to do well. During undergrad, students are given several opportunities throughout the year to boost or make up grades through midterm tests, assignments, essays, and final exams. Contrastingly, law school presents only one or two opportunities to grade students, which illustrates how high the stakes are as it leaves little room for error (5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the sense of competition increases the anxiety which a lot of students face since everyone around you poses as a rival. Undergrad has thousands of people, all of whom are enrolled in different programs with different focuses and goals. Contrastingly, in law school, limited enrolment of students grants entry to a small pool of candidates, and everyone has one goal, to be work for a prestigious law firm while standing out from the rest. Although the sense of competition can be used as motivation to help some reach their full potential, for others it can take a negative toll on their mental health (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study found that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;students were comparing themselves to others and then feeling deficient, like they were the only ones who didn’t understand something or were the only ones who were struggling. It was usually related to a sense of not being good enough academically (5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling the toxic culture of comparison actively lowers people’s self-esteem and may lead individuals to indulge in unhealthy habits. Research has shown that addiction in the legal profession stems from law school where people feel the pressure to compete and eventually resort to drugs and alcohol to cope (6). A wide variety of drugs, especially cocaine, are used to keep overworked students alert to prevent them from falling behind or losing precious time through sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the cut-throat competition can make one feel isolated, it is essential to realize everyone is in the same boat, especially in the first year of law school. All students are bound to struggle, and no one should feel ashamed for feeling stressed or seeking professional help. To ease into the lifestyle and stressful conditions of law schools, students are encouraged to take part in pre-law societies and similar organizations to take part in conversations related to law with like-minded people (4). It allows an individual to candidly talk to like-minded people and make friends with those who have similar goals and interest. Some law societies also connect you to current and former law students in informal settings, which can go a far way in helping students in seeking opportunities in the future. Given the way law school is isolating from one’s family and friends, making connections through such extracurricular clubs with people who are undergoing similar circumstances serves to help one feel heard and understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CDTALaw, “Family, Stress and 1Ls” California Desert Trial Academy College of Law, February 24, 2021. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdtalaw.com/cdta/family-stress-1ls/&quot;&gt;https://cdtalaw.com/cdta/family-stress-1ls/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How Hard is Law School? 5 Differences Between Law School and Undergrad”, University of Buffalo School of Law, August 6, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.law.buffalo.edu/blog/5_differences_between_law_school_and_undergrad.html&quot;&gt;https://www.law.buffalo.edu/blog/5_differences_between_law_school_and_undergrad.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“How to Deal with Law School Stress in Healthy Ways.” New England Law Boston. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nesl.edu/blog/detail/how-to-deal-with-law-school-stress-in-healthy-ways&quot;&gt;https://www.nesl.edu/blog/detail/how-to-deal-with-law-school-stress-in-healthy-ways&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Joanna Hughes, “Four Tips for Transitioning from College to Law School” Keystone Law, January 3, 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lawstudies.com/article/four-tips-for-transitioning-from-college-to-law-school/&quot;&gt;https://www.lawstudies.com/article/four-tips-for-transitioning-from-college-to-law-school/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matthew Jenkin, “Legally drained: why are stress levels rising among law students?” The Guardian, November 19, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/law/2019/nov/19/legally-drained-why-are-stress-levels-rising-among-law-students&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/law/2019/nov/19/legally-drained-why-are-stress-levels-rising-among-law-students&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NYC, Psychiatry. “The Severity of Drug Addiction in the Legal Profession.” Fifth Avenue Psychiatry, April 23, 2019. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychiatrynyc.com/blog/the-severity-of-drug-addiction-in-lawyers/&quot;&gt;https://www.psychiatrynyc.com/blog/the-severity-of-drug-addiction-in-lawyers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roger Whittler, “Managing stress in law school and beyond”, The Missouri Bar, November 18, 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.mobar.org/managing-stress-in-law-school-and-beyond/&quot;&gt;https://news.mobar.org/managing-stress-in-law-school-and-beyond/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Author&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myra Mansoor&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>